[Music]
frankincense and myrrh date back to
thousands of years before the three wise
men the burning of witches incense may
have actually had a hygienic function
like maybe repelling mosquitoes and when
put to the test incense fumes were able
to kill off some bacteria and mold in
the air but may also carry health risks
although the adverse health effects of
secondhand tobacco smoke are well
recognized the impact of burning incense
in the home has received less attention
but burning incense has been found to
generate like four times the particulate
matter is cigarettes so incense may be
even worse no wonder home incense use
may have significant adverse health
effects particularly on the heart and
lungs including childhood asthma
no wonder since the incense smoke
particle size peaks down in the danger
range so ultra refined they can float
down to the deepest parts of the lungs
it's not just the little ash particles
in the smoke though there's carbon
monoxide nitric oxides sulfur dioxide
carcinogenic polycyclic aromatic
hydrocarbons and volatile organic
compounds like benzene and formaldehyde
the world health organization suggests
limiting indoor formaldehyde to about 80
parts per billion but even with a window
open during the hour or so incense is
burning formaldehyde levels exceed the
safety limit
what does this all mean in terms of
disease outcomes
studies on rats show incense can do all
sorts of terrible things but what about
people
a study of thousands of children
followed over time found that exposure
to household incense burning was
associated with impaired lung function
reduced lung function growth and
increased risks of respiratory diseases
and symptoms
daily exposure is associated with
impaired lung function in adolescents
too though interestingly those who had
pets at home appeared to have better
lung function
something i noted previously how having
a dog or cat in the house during early
life may protect against childhood
asthma analogy
what about the heart
long-term exposure to incense burning in
the home environment was associated with
an increased risk of cardiovascular
mortality
approximately eight percent of heart
disease deaths and 12 percent of stroke
deaths could potentially be attributed
to incense use
though they were looking at long-term
exposure so like
incense burning at home on a daily basis
for more than 20 years
what about cancer
temple workers exposed to incense day in
and day out were found to have evidence
of significantly more dna damage
including dna strand breaks does this
translate into greater cancer risk
one unsolved mystery has been why
non-smoking asian women have such high
lung cancer rates might it be incense
probably not since the association
between incense use and lung cancer
remains inconclusive though incense use
does appear to be linked to cancers of
the upper respiratory tract as well as
brain tumors among children whose
mothers were exposed to incense
three times the odds even more than that
of secondhand smoke in fact even more
than the consumption of bologna
sandwiches processed meat consumption
only appears to at most double brain
tumor risk among children
even without tumors a study of 15 000
infants found that household incense
burning was associated with a delay in
brain development milestones such as
when they start to walk
and then on the other side of the life
cycle incense exposure among older
adults was associated with reduced
cognitive performance and adverse
structural changes in the brain
the researchers conclude that this calls
for safer practices such as avoiding
burning incense indoors or using safer
incense alternatives
so-called environmentally friendly types
of incense have been put to the test and
they were found to contain even higher
concentrations of several potentially
carcinogenic polycyclic aromatic
hydrocarbons despite being a recognized
health hazard burning incense remains in
widespread use in the very least we may
want to avoid burning incense in the
home when susceptible individuals are
present such as the very young the very
old or people with a family history of
allergies or pre-existing cardiovascular
or respiratory disease
one innovative suggestion is electronic
incense like the e-cigarette of the
incense world so you get the fragrance
without the combustion byproducts of
smoke
most of the concern about
e-cigarette-related adverse events
traditionally have evolved around the
nicotine which wouldn't be a problem
with e-incense the concern that
e-cigarette use would lead to real
cigarette use
but now that there have been thousands
of cases of lung injury associated with
vaping and we're still actually not sure
what's causing the issue it seems to me
we should figure that out before we push
for the electronic incense equivalent
one option in the meantime is scented
candles which under normal conditions of
use do not appear to pose known health
risks to the consumer
[Music]
you